[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-
radio.net SC radio is brought to you by
the it computer society and by It
software Magazine online at computer.org
[Music]
software this is Jeremy Jung for
software engineering radio today I'm
talking to Hong mini he is the developer
of Fifi a typescript library for
building activity Pub server
applications Hong welcome to software
engineering radio thank you for having
me the first thing I think we should
start with is defining activity Pub what
is activity Pub activity Pub is the
protocol that lets social networks talk
to each other and is officially
recommended by WCC is what powers this
thing we call the Fedor which is
basically a way for different social
media platforms to work together can you
give some examples that people might
have heard of of either users of
activity Pub or things that are a part
of this ferse masteron is probably the
biggest one out there and you know
what's interesting mastera thre has
actually started implementing activity
pop this summer so this still pretty
much a oneway St right now in East Asia
especially Japan there's this really
popular micro blogging platform called
misy it's got so many Forks that people
actually joke around and call them
forkys but it's not just about Twitter
style micro bloging there's pixel Fred
which is kind of like Instagram but for
the fedar and the same Fox recently
launched Loops which is basically doing
what Tik Tok does but in the FED verse
then you've got stuff like Lami and amb
which are doing the r thing in the FED
verse oh like redit yeah there are so
much more out there that I haven't even
mentioned most of it is open source
which is pretty cool so the first few
examples you gave mastadon
and meta's threads they're very similar
to Twitter right so that's what you were
calling the micro blogging applications
and I think what you had said which is a
little bit interesting is you had said
meta threads is only one way so could
you kind of describe like what you mean
by that currently metast only can be
followed by other activity PP
applications but you can follow other
people in in the FED virs people who are
using another micro blogging platform
like Mastadon can follow someone on
meta's threads platform but the other
way is not true if you're on threads you
can't follow someone on Mastadon yes
that's right and that's not a limitation
of the protocol itself that's a design
decision or a decision made by meta yeah
they slowly implementing activity pop
and I hope they will implement complete
activity p in the future and then the
other examples you gave one is I believe
it was Pixel fed very similar to
Instagram and then the last examples you
gave was I think it was lemy you said
it's similar to Reddit cuz you mentioned
the term fediverse before and you
mentioned that these all use activity
Pub and since these seem like different
kinds of applications what does it mean
for them to interact because with
Macedon and threads I can kind of
understand because they're both similar
to Twitter so you're posting messages
and replying but what does it mean for
example for someone on Mastadon to
interact with someone on lemi which is
like Reddit because they seem very
different people in Lei and Mastodon are
called actors and they can follow each
other they have interactions between
them called activities there are several
types of activities like create follow
undo like and so on so activity pop
applications tend to use this vocabulary
to implement their features so for
example lemi uses like activities for
uping and this like activities for down
booing and is trans related to likes in
masteron so if you saw me a post on Lami
and it show up on your masterdom
timeline if you like that post is ooting
in Lei and probably similarly with pixel
fed which you said is like Instagram if
you follow someone's pixel fed account
in Macedon and they post a photo in
pixel fed they would see it as a post in
Mastadon natively and they could give it
a like there yes and these activities
that you mentioned so the like and the
dislike are those part of activity Pub
itself yes okay and this vocabulary can
be extended so you can add additional
actions or are you adding information to
the existing actions it's called
activity vocabulary there are things
like accept add announce AR right bra
create delete dislike flag follow ignore
invite join and so on so basically
almost everything you need to build
social media is already there in the
vocabulary but if you want to extend
some more you can Define your own
vocabulary most most of the things that
an Instagram or a Twitter or a Reddit
would need is already there but you're
saying that you can have your own
vocabulary so if there's an action or an
activity that is not covered by the
specification you can create one
yourself yes for example misy and ploma
defined Emoji reactor to represent Emoji
reactions because the systems can extend
the vocabulary
what are some other examples of cases
where Mastadon or any other of these
systems has found that the existing
vocabulary is not enough what are some
other examples of applications extending
it for example Mastodon Define suspended
suspended yeah suspended property they
are not activities but they are
properties in the activity activity P
consists of s types objects and there
are activities and noral objects like
article they can have properties and
there are several existing properties
but they can be also extended so
masteron extended some properties they
need so for example they Define
suspended or discover
discoverable yeah suspended to tell if
an Ator is suspended by moderators this
discoverable tells if an actor itself
wants to be search it and index it there
are much more properties masteron
extended these are properties of the
actor these are properties of the user
yes actors cuz I think earlier you
mentioned that the concept of a user is
an actor and it sounds like what you're
saying is an actor can have all these
properties there's probably a username
and things like that but Mastadon has
extended the properties so that you can
have a property on whether you want to
be searched or indexed you can have a
property that says you're suspended so I
guess your account is still there but
can't be used anymore more yes something
we should probably talk about then is so
you have these actors you have these
activities that I'm assuming the actors
are performing on one another what does
that data look like and what does the
communication look like actors have
their own D reference of URI and when
you look up that URI you get all the
info about the actor in Json LD format
Json LD yeah Json LD link Data actor has
all the stuff you expect to find on a
Social account name bio URL to the
profit page profit picture header image
and more there are five main types of
actors application group organization
person and service and you know how
sometimes on masteron USC on account
Market as a b a b yeah B and that's why
what an actor of type service looks like
and the activity Prospect actually let
you create other types Beyond these five
but I haven't seen anymore actually do
that yet and you mentioned that these
are all Json objects but the LD part the
link data part I'm not familiar with so
what is different about the link data
part of the Json Json LD is the special
way of writing rdf which was originally
used in the cement web usually Alf uses
format it's called Trippers triples yeah
subject predicate and object subject
predicate object can you give an example
of what those three would be for example
is a person it's a Tripper John is a
subject and is a predicate is is the
predicate okay and person is a object
that's great for showing how things are
connected but it's pretty different from
how we usually handle data in rest for
apis and stuff like normally we say a
person object has property like name do
bio and so on and a bunch of subject
predicate object Trippers that's where J
comes in it's designed to look more like
the Json we are used to work with while
still being able to represent rdf graphs
rdf graph what is that rdf graphs are
ontology ontology yeah yeah it's a way
to represent factual data but it's quite
different from how we represent data in
relational database it's a bunch of
Trippers each subject and objects are no
and predic case connect this no you
mentioned the semantic web what does
that mean what is the semantic web it's
a way to represent web in the structural
way is much readable so that you can
scan the data in the web using Scrappers
or cros scrapers or crawling okay yeah
yeah then you can have a graph data of
web and you can qu information about
things from the data so is the web as it
exists now is that the semantic web or
is it something different I think it's
partially stic web you have several
metadata in your HTML for example there
are s specification for cement web
like open graph metadata because when I
think about open graph I think about the
metadata on a web page that tells other
applications or websites that if you
link to this page show this image or
show this title and description you're
saying that specifically you consider
part of the semantic web that's so
semantic web to make your website stic
web your website should be able to
provide structural data and other people
can make Scrappers to scan structural
data from your website there are bunch
of attributes and tex for HTML to
represent metadata for example you have
relation attribute real so if you have a
link
with rare equal me to your another
social profile then other people can
tell Two web pages represent the same
person oh I see so you could have more
than one website maybe one is your blog
and maybe one is your favorite birds or
something like that but you could put a
relation tag in both the real tag with
information about you as a person so
that someone who scrapes both websites
could look at that tag and see that both
of these websites are by H by this
person yeah I think Json L is designed
for stic we but in reality activity pop
implementations the most of them are not
aware of seaware the choice of Json link
data the Json LD by
the people who made the specification
they had this idea that things that
implemented activity Pub would be a part
of this semantic web but the actual
implementation of a Mastadon or a pixel
fed they use Json LD because it's part
of the specification but the way they
use it it it ends up not really being a
part of this semantic web yeah that's
exactly you've mentioned that
implementing it is difficult
what makes implementing Json LD
particularly hard the Json LD spec is
complex which is why a lot of
programming languages don't even have
JSL implementations and it's pretty slow
compared to just working with a regular
Json so what happen is a lot of activity
P implementations just treat jonl like
is regular J without using a proper jsld
process cessor you can do that but it
creates all sort of heada in JD there's
are weird equivalencies like if a
property is missing or if it's an empty
array that means the same thing or if a
property has one value versus an array
with just that one value in it same
thing so when you're writing code to
pass J you've got to keep checking if
something's an array how long it is and
all that is super easy to mess up it's
not just reading JSL that's tricky
creating it is just as bad like you
might forget to include the right
context metadata for a vocabulary and
end up with a JSL document that's either
invalid or means something totally
different from what you wanted even the
activity power implementations meth this
pretty often with faty we've got a JSL
process built in and we keep running
into issues where major activity power
implementations create invalided Json LD
we've had to create workarounds for all
of them but it's not pretty and the cost
kind of will miss even though there is a
specification for Json LD it sounds like
the implement ERS don't necessarily
follow it so you are kind of parsing
Json LD but not really you're parsing
something that looks like Json LD but
isn't quite it yes that's right and is
that true in the biggest implementations
Macedon for example are there things
that it sends and its activities that
aren't valid Jason LD those
implementations that had bad J LD tends
to fix them soon as a possible but
regulations are so often made a yeah
even within Mastadon which is probably
one of the largest implementers of
activity PB there are cases where it's
not valid Json LD and somebody fixes it
but then later on there are other
messages or other activities that were
valid but aren't valid anymore and so
it's this back and forth of fixing them
and causing new issues it sounds like
yeah yeah right yeah that sounds very
difficult to deal with yeah yeah yeah
we've been talking about the messages
themselves are this special format of
Jason that's very particular but how do
these instances communicate with one
another most of time it all starts with
a f like when John follows Alis then
Alice as both John and John's inbox URI
to her follows list and after John
follow at whenever Alis post something
new that activist get sent to John's
inbox beyond the scenes this is just an
HTTP post request even though activity
Pub is built on HTTP it doesn't really
care about the HTP resp P Beyond did it
work or not if you want to reply to an
activity you need to figure out the
senders inbox URI and send the reply
activity there if we Define all the
terms there's the actor which is the
person each actor can send different
activities those activities are in the
form of a Json link data yeah and
everybody has an inbox and an inbox is
an HTTP URL that people post to right
and so when you think about that you had
mentioned that if you have a list of
followers let's say you have 100
followers would that mean that you have
the URLs to all a hundred of those
followers inboxes and that you would
send one HTTP post to each inbox every
time you had a new message pretty much
our activity implementations have a
thing called shared inbox is exactly
what it sounds like one inbox that are
actors on a sub share private stuff like
DMS don't go there is just for public
post and thoughts I think we haven't
really talked about the fact that when
you have multiple users usually they're
on a server right that somebody chooses
so you could have tens of thousands I
don't know how many people can fit on
the same server but rather than
you having to post to each user
individually you can post to the shared
inbox on This Server so let's say of
your 100 followers 50 of them are on the
same server and you have a new post you
only need to post to the shared inbox
once yes that's right in that message
you would I assume have links to each of
the profiles or actors that you wanted
to send that message to yeah something
that I've seen in the past is there are
people who have challenges with
scaling their Mastadon instance or their
implementations of activity Pub as the
the number of followers grow I've seen a
post about ghost one of the companies
you work with mentioning that they've
had challenges there what are the
challenges there and and how do you
think those can be resolved to put this
in context when ghost mentioned the
scaling is they were not using message
cues yet I'm pretty sure using message
CU would have a lot of their scaling
problems that say it's definitely true
that a lot of activity P software has
trouble with scaring right now I think
part of the problem is that everyone's
using this purely event driven approach
to sending activities around one of the
big issues is that when they delivery
fails is the sender who has to try not
the reer plus those are this overhead
because the sender has to authenticate
itself with HTP signatures every time
actually the activity PP suggests using
ping too so I'd love to see more
activity po s try using both approaches
together you mean the
followers would pull who they're
following instead of the person posting
the messages having to send their posts
to everyone's inboxes I see yeah so
that's a part of the activity Pub
specification but not implemented in a
lot of activity pup
implementations yes it sounds like maybe
that puts a lot of burden on the servers
that have people with a lot of followers
because they have to post to every
single follower server and maybe the
server is slow or they can't reach it
and like you said they have to just keep
trying and trying there could be a lot
of challenges there yes right we've
talked a little bit about the fact that
each actor is hosted by a server and
those servers can host multiple actors
but if you want to move to another
server either because your server is
shutting down or you just would like to
change servers what are some of the
challenges there activity pop and fed
already have the specification for
account move is called Fe
7628 move Ator first thing you need to
do when moving on account is prove that
both the old and new accounts belong to
the same part you do this by adding the
old accounts actor UI to the new
accounts also known as property then all
the cont test all the other instances is
moving by sending out a move activity
when a server gets this move activity it
checks that both accounts really do
belong to the same part and in Max all
the accounts that were following the old
account start following the new one
instead that's how the new account gets
to keep or the old account follow us
pretty much all the major activity po
software has this feature built in for
example masteron MSY you name it this is
very similar to The Post where when you
execute a move the server that
originally hosted that actor they need
to somehow tell every single other
server that was following that account
that you've moved and so if there's any
issues with communicating with one of
those servers or you miss one then it
just won't recognize that you've moved
you have to make sure that you you talk
to every single server that's right I
could see how that could be a difficult
problem sometimes if you have a lot of
followers yeah you've created a
typescript library FiFi for building
activity Pub powered applications what
was the reason you decided to create
fify
fify is activity pop serers framework I
built for typescript it basically takes
away a lot of headaches you get trying
to implement activity pop Ser from
scratch the whole thing started because
I wanted to build horo single user
microing platform I built but when I
tried to implement activity pop from
ground up it was kind of a nightmare
imagine trying to write a CGI program in
po or C back in the late '90s where you
are manually printing out HTP headers
and HTML ASB there just wasn't any good
ab session layer to go with there were
already some libraries and Frameworks
for activity pop out there but none of
them really hit the Swift spot I was
looking for they were either to high
level and re it like you could only
build a masteron clone they barely did
anything at all or they were not written
in language I didn't really know I saw
that you are doing some work with ghost
how is Ghost using fify ghost is an open
source publishing platform they have put
some money into pfy which is why I get
to work on it full time now there are
activ power feature is still in private
beta but it should be available to
everyone pretty soon we work together to
improve faty basically they are user of
faty they
report box request new features to fify
then I fix them or Implement them first
ghost to my understanding is a blogging
platform and a a newsletter platform so
what does it mean for them to implement
activity Pub what would somebody using
Mastadon for example get when they
follow somebody using ghost
ghost will have pedb handle for their
each blog if you follow them in your
masteron or something like then a new
post is published these post will show
up your timeline in masteron and you can
like them or share them and in the
dashboard of ghost you can see who like
their post or shared their post and so
on is pretty like how Master Works about
in ghost I see so if you are writing a
ghost blog and somebody follows your
blog from Mastadon sort of like we were
talking about earlier they can like your
post and on the blog itself you could
show oh I have 200 likes and those
aren't necessarily people who were on
your ghost website they could be people
that were liking your post from Mastadon
yes something you mentioned at the
beginning was there is a community of
developers in in Asia making Forks of I
believe of Macedon right yeah do you
have experience working in that
development Community what's different
about it compared to the more Western
Centric Community they are very similar
in most ways the key difference is a
language of course they communicate in
Japanese primarily they also accept
Prest with English but there are tons of
comments in Japanese in their code so
you need to translate them into English
or your first language to understand
what code does so I think that makes
betterer for Western developers in fact
many Western developers that contribute
to mki or fory are able to speak or
little Japanese I think and many of
developers of MSY and forus are kind of
otak oh otaku okay it's not a big de but
you can see difference in a GL Yeah you
mentioned one of the things that I
believe MSY implemented was the Emoji
reactions and maybe one of the reasons
they wanted that was so that they could
react to each other's posts with you
know anime pictures or things like that
yeah
yeah you've mentioned misy and fory so
is is misy a fork of Macedon and then is
forky a fork of misy no MSY is not a
fork of Mason is from Scrat it's its own
implementation and Fork Cas are Forks of
madon oh I see I see but both of those
are primarily built by Japanese
developers yes whereas maon is written
in Ruby Ruby on R but m is built in
typescript and because of
activity Pub they all implement it so
you can communicate with people between
Macedon and m key because they all
understand the same
activities yes you did mention since
there are extensions like misy has the
Emoji reactions when there is an
activity that an implementation doesn't
support what happens between the two
servers do you send it to a server's
inbox and then the server just doesn't
do anything with it so implementers
consider backward compatibility so they
designed to work it with other
implementation that doesn't support that
activity for example misy uses like
activity for emoj reaction so if you put
on emoi to a masteron post then in
masteron you get one like so it's in
intended behavior of by MSY developers
that they fall back to normal rights but
sometimes activity power Implement us
introduce a new entirely
new activity type for example ploma
introduce Emoji react and if you put
Emoji reaction to masteron post from
proma in masteron you have nothing to
see because Mason just ignores them if I
understand correctly both m key and
ploma are independent implementations of
activity Pub but with miskey their
message is backwards compatible where
it's if you don't understand the Emoji
reaction it'll be embedded inside of a
like message whereas with ploma they
send an activity that masdon can't
understand at all so it just doesn't do
anything yes right but MSY also
understand Emoji re activity so between
proma and MSY they have exchange Emoji
reactions with no problem oh I see so
they both understand that activity they
both implement it the same way but then
when misy communicates with masted on or
with an instance that it knows doesn't
understand it it sends something
different yeah that's right the servers
can they query one another to know which
activities they support usually activity
P implementation also Implement node
info specification node info yeah it's
like usual agent like seeing in
fediverse so implementations tell the
other instance is masteron or something
other you can quy the type of server
okay so within activity Pub are each of
the servers is the term node is that
word they use for each server yes right
you have the nodes which can have any
number of actors and the servers send
activities to one another to each
other's inboxes so those are all the I
guess the way they all communicate yeah
you've implemented activity pub with
fify because you found like there
weren't good enough implementations or
resources already
did you implement it based off of the
specification or did you look at
existing implementations while you were
building your
implementation to be honest instead of
just diving into the spec I usually
start by looking at actually activity
pops of T code first the activity pops
Peg is also value that you can really
build something just from reading it so
when we talk about activity pop we are
actually talking about a whole bunch of
other technical standards too we finger
HP signatures and more so you need to
understand all of this DOA as well with
the specification alone you were saying
it's too vague and so what ends up
being I'm not sure if it's right to call
it a spec but looking at the
implementations that people have already
made that collectively becomes the spec
because trying to follow the spec just
by itself is maybe too difficult yes
maybe that brings up the issues you were
talking about before where you have
specifications like Json LD where
they're so complicated that even the
biggest implementations aren't quite
following it exactly yeah if somebody
wanted to get started with understanding
a little bit more about activity Pub or
or building something with it where
would you recommend they start I
to dig into a lot of code from actual
implementations first masteron MSY eoma
and so on there are also some really
cool tools that have been SP helpful for
example activity pop Academy is this
awesome masteron server for debugging
activity pop it makes it sport is to
create a temporary account and see what
activities are going back and forth
there's also browse pop browse PP is
this NE tool for looking up and browsing
activity pop objects it's really handy
when you want to see how different
activity po software handles various
features I also recommend to use faty
I've got to mention the fify sharei
which comes with some really useful
tools so if someone uses fify they're
writing an application in typescript
then it sounds like they have to know
the highlevel concepts they have to know
what are the different activities what
is inside of an actor but the actual
implementation of how do I create and
parse Json link data those kinds of
things are taken care of by the library
yes yes right in some ways it seems like
it might be good to like you were saying
use the tools you mentioned to create a
test Macedon account look at the
messages being sent back and forth and
then when you're trying to implement it
starting with something like Fifi might
be good because then you can really just
focus on the concepts and not worry so
much about the implementation details
yes that's right is there anything else
you wanted to mention or or thought we
should have talked about I want to talk
about a lot of stuff of activity P but
it's difficult to speak in English for
me so it's a shame to talk talk about it
very later we need everybody to learn
Korean
right yes please well I want to thank
you for taking the time I know it must
have been really challenging to give an
interview in you know a language that's
not your native one so thank you for
spending the time to talk with me thank
you for having me this has been Jeremy
Jung for software engineering radio
thanks for
listening thanks for listening to SC
radio an educational program brought to
you by I software magazine for more
about the podcast including other
episodes visit our website at se-
radio.net to provide feedback you can
comment on each episode on the website
or reach us on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter
or through our slack Channel at
seo. slack.com you can also email us at
team
e-r. this and all other episodes of SC
radio is licensed under Creative Commons
license
2.5 thanks for listening